<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exceeding joyfull nevvs from Lincoln-shire. Or The resolution of the gentry and commonalty, inhabiting in the county of Lineoln [sic], concerning the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and the high court of Parliament. Also joyfull nevves from Leicester declaring how Mr Henry Hastings was taken prisoner by the High-Sheriffe of the said county, on Sunday, August 14. 1642. Whereunto is annexed the resolution of the Lords and Commons assembled in this present Parliament, concerning the Kings most Excellent Majesty. Ordered that this be printed and published. Joh. Browne, Cler. Parl.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E112_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862644</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862644</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114810</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84246)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114810)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 20:E112[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exceeding joyfull nevvs from Lincoln-shire. Or The resolution of the gentry and commonalty, inhabiting in the county of Lineoln [sic], concerning the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and the high court of Parliament. Also joyfull nevves from Leicester declaring how Mr Henry Hastings was taken prisoner by the High-Sheriffe of the said county, on Sunday, August 14. 1642. Whereunto is annexed the resolution of the Lords and Commons assembled in this present Parliament, concerning the Kings most Excellent Majesty. Ordered that this be printed and published. Joh. Browne, Cler. Parl.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Fowler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Aug. 17. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Loughborough, Henry Hastings, --  Baron, 1610-1667 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lincolnshire (England) --  History, Military --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114810:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EXCEEDING JOYFULL NEWS FROM LINCOLN-SHIRE.</p>
            <p>OR The Reſolution of the Gentry and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, inhabiting in the County of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, and the High Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>ALSO JOYFVLL NEVVES FROM LEICESTER Declaring how <hi>Mr Henry Haſtings</hi> was taken priſoner by the High-Sheriffe of the ſaid County, on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> Auguſt 14. 1642.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed the Reſolution of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in this preſent Parliament, concerning the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Ordered that this be printed and publiſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Joh. Browne, Cler. Parl.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Fowler.</hi> Aug. 17. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb facs="tcp:114810:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114810:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Joyfull Newes</hi> FROM Lincolne-ſhire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Inhabitants of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> having by their Petitions to the high Court of Parliament, declared their hearty affections to them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring them to goe on with confidence, promiſing them that their Lives, eſtates, and all they could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſhould be laid downe at their Feet.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe their Petition preſented to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie at <hi>Yorke,</hi> wherein they humbly intreated his Majeſty to returne to his Parliament, declaring the great miſery, &amp; apparent troubles that were like to enſue, and fall upon this Kingdome, if his Majeſty ſhould any longer deny his gratious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Royall aſſent to his high Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, wherein they declared the depth of their affections to the Parliament, and their earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb facs="tcp:114810:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſerve the peace of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe they having received an Anſwer to their Petition, were reviled by the Cavaliers, and called <hi>Round-heads,</hi> with other abuſes not fit to be mentioned. At their returne from <hi>Yorke</hi> they by order of the Committee of Parliament aſſembled to put the Ordinance of <hi>Militia</hi> in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, where there were aſſembled many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands to the great admiration and not little ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Lieutenants of the Shire that were appointed by the Parliament to ſee the ſaid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance put in execution.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe they then gave ſuch large teſtimonies of his love and obedience to the Parliament, that the Committee thought it neceſſary to give im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation thereof to the Houſe, who returned them thankes for the ſame, animating them on to a continuance in the ſame duty.</p>
            <p>Which they had great reaſon to do, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that very inſtant Officers appointed by His Majeſty to put the commiſſion of Aray in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Nevertheleſſe, though His Majeſties Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers had put up the Proclamation concerning His Majeſties diſavowing the ordinance of the <hi>Militia,</hi> withall giving ſtrict command in His Majeſties name, that they ſhould not yeeld obedience to the ſaid Ordinance, they ſtill with chearfulneſſe purſued in the due execution of the ſame.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty finding that his expectation was made fruſtrate and that he could not prevail with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114810:3"/>his officers (being councelled thereto by the Lord <hi>Mowbray</hi>) was reſolved to goe in perſon to put the commiſſion of <hi>Aray</hi> in execution.</p>
            <p>Where being arived, he by his ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand cauſed the gentry and cominalty of the ſaid Countie to be ſummoned, who according to their Loyalty and Allegiance obeyed His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties command.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of which they have undergone ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cenſures, ſome calling them <hi>Turne-coats,</hi> and many other ignominious names.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe they thought it convenient to declare their Reſolution concerning their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to His Majeſty, and their duty to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>For their obedience to His Majeſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they declare that it ſtood not with their loyalties to ſtand in flat oppoſition to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties commands, (His Majeſty commanding nothing which intrenched upon the Peace of the Kingdome, or the priviledge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) Withall they doe declare, that if His Majeſty ſhall command them, they will march with him, and obey his juſt commands, as loyall and obedient Subjects.</p>
            <p>But likewiſe they are reſolved ſo farre to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their duty to the Parliament, that if his Majeſty, in his owne perſon, or by his miniſters, ſhall command them to put any thing in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Parliament, or imploy any others
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114810:4"/>of His Majeſties Forces in any ſuch deſign; that then they will not onely forbeare the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of any ſuch act themſelves, but alſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard then lives in oppoſing of all ſuch as ſhall any way indeavour the ſame.</p>
            <p>Promiſing that they ſhall no longer wiſh a godly neace, a freedome in Religion, nor the ſweet enjoyment of ought that is good or deare unto them, then they ſhall continue faithfull to the commands of the high Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>This is the Reſolution of the Gentry and Commonalty of <hi>Lincolneſhire,</hi> which I have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for the ſatisfaction of the world, it being related to me by a Gentleman of good worth of the ſame County.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe a Letter was ſent from <hi>Leiceſter</hi> to a Merchant of this City, declaring how Maſter <hi>Haſtings</hi> with <hi>a</hi> Troop of Cavaliers went up againſt the High Sheriffe of the ſaid County, with an intent to have burnt his houſe; but the High Sheriffe having notice thereof, ſummoned ſome Troops of Horſe, which were raiſed ſince theſe troubles began in the Kingdome; and three miles from <hi>Langborough,</hi> fell upon him, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led eight of his men, and tooke him, and ſome other of his Cavaliers: which he having done, ſent him to the City of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi> But on the way Colonel <hi>Lunsford</hi> met with him, having a ſtrong party, and worſted them, taking the ſaid <hi>Haſtings</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114810:4"/>away before the Countrey could come in to their reſcue. Nevertheleſſe they were forced to fly as faſt as their legs could carry them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe it is reſolved upon the Queſtion by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that in caſe any Force be brought out of one County into another County of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to diſturbe the peace of the Kingdome, that the Lord Lieutenants and the Deputy Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants of the Counties adjoyning, be required to give aid and aſſiſtance to the ſaid Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants or Deputy Lieutenants requiring the ſame, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Parliamentary_resolution">
            <head>The Parliaments RESOL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION, Concerning the Kings moſt Excellent MAJESTY.</head>
            <p>THE Lords and Commons to witneſſe their conſtant and unſhaken loyalty and affection to his Majeſty, do ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that if his Majeſty ſhall immediately disband
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114810:5"/>all his Forces; and be pleaſed to abandon all thoſe wicked Counſells, and leave them to condigne puniſhment and returne and hearken to the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome advice of his great Counſell, they will real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour to make both his Majeſty and his Poſterity, as great, rich, and potent, as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved at home and feared abroad, as any Prince that ever ſwayed this Scepter, which is their firm and conſtant Reſolution.</p>
            <div type="license">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Auguſt the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1642.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, that this Declaration be forthwith Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and publiſhed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hen. Elſyng Cler. Parl. Do. Com.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
